Hello, and welcome back to
part two of how to prepare for
your chemistry lab practical.
So in this particular set of the
videos, we're going to, rather than go
into the conditions of the practical,
we're going to be going through every
lab and talk about kind of the major
things that I would recommend studying
for as we go through the practical.
So one thing is you do need to study
for this, just like any normal exam,
even though it is a lab based exam.
You know, a lot of people are like,
Oh, how do you study for a practical?
The best thing for you to do is to review
your, mainly review the introductions
of your different procedures.
And then I would recommend like
flipping through the data sets to see
like, okay, what did you calculate?
Especially those older labs from
the beginning of the semester.
Some of them you haven't really, you
haven't seen in maybe two or three months.
So it's really easy to forget
some of those core concepts.
So go through them, flip
through them, see what they are.
And I would practice some of the post
lab questions and some of the data workup
you did and make sure you're getting the
same numbers that you got from before.
That's the best way to practice.
Now the other things is as
we go through these videos.
So as you're watching this, either,
either via canvas or on YouTube.
Um, if you're on YouTube, I did
mark each individual experiment,
which I'm referring to for you to
kind of see what I'm talking about.
So if you're only looking
for specific ones.
You can kind of scroll through that
and look for them specifically.
Um, and just as a final, like, you
know, as a little warning, this, I'm
not going to say every single detail,
which could be on that practical.
If we were to do that, this
video would be hours long.
There could, there obviously could
be more and every teacher's going
to test you on different things.
So these are just the major things I
would recommend knowing, and they're
going to help you with your final exam
and maybe even your last exam too.
So it's going to help you
with all kinds of things.
So let's take a look at each exam
and see, or sorry, each lab and
see exactly how we would prepare.
The first experiment that you
performed was making measurements
back in week, week one or week two of
your semester, a very long time ago.
So with this lab, it went over
some core concepts that were used
throughout the entire semester.
The biggest thing was is you need
to learn how to make different
measurements of mass, volume, and length.
So when we're making those measurements,
the biggest thing is when you're taking
your practical, you need to record all of
your significant figures and your units
when you are writing down your answers.
If you do not write one of those
things, you might lose points on
questions, and you might have got
the answer right, but you didn't
write your units or show your work.
So make sure you write
all those things down.
They're very important.
So when you're writing anything down
from the balance, include all the digits.
If you're measuring a volume, you've
got to read your tick marks correctly.
So for example, I included a
ruler here just to kind of go
through, like, how would you do it.
So I put like a little block here,
which you had to measure that first lab.
So if I were to do this, how
exactly would you go about it?
So right now I have the block
going between one and two.
So if we were to kind of look at this
thing, you can see, okay, there's 0.
1, 0.
2, 0.
3, 4, 5, 6, 7, right?
So the block ends at about 0 or 0.
7 is where the difference
is in that measurement.
So is that all you would put though?
So the one thing you got to
remember is that there was certain.
Digits.
So what you can see via the tick
marks, and then you could always
estimate one beyond that tick mark.
So that last digit is fully up
to you what you want to place,
but you need to include it.
So even though at 0.
7, you, in this case, you'd have to put 0.
70 to indicate the SIG figs, right?
Trailing zeros are significant.
So you need to place them.
It matters, right?
If you are using a very accurate piece of
equipment, you need to illustrate that and
showcase that in your, in your vocabulary.
I'm going to be kind of listing here
is like all the important videos and
concepts and things that we, that me,
I made me made other videos on that you
can refer to if you'd like, I'm going
to put them in the description too.
So that way you can refer to them as
well in the YouTube video description.
So the biggest thing is the
displacement method was one
of the things that you used.
So you all, you measured the volume via
length, but you also did the density
by doing the displacement method too.
So the one thing is when we went
over density, is what we refer
to as an intrinsic property.
And you're like, Oh crap,
I forgot about this stuff.
So this meant that no matter what
the mass was or the volume, it
would always have the same density.
It does not change.
So when, uh, essentially like a
couple months ago, I made different
videos on how to go over this.
One was what is density, which
just goes over the basic ideas.
The other one was a displacement method
video, which actually goes through
examples of this lab of how to show
how to, how to calculate these things.
So when we're doing a displacement
method, it's actually quite simple.
So the whole idea is just to kind
of scroll down here for a second.
Was, essentially you were taking a
graduated cylinder with some water
in it and you were dropping an
object into the grad cylinder and
it displaced the volume of liquid.
So one thing that it allows you to do
is, if you can remember, density is grams
over milliliters or mass over volume.
So what you can do is if you measure
the mass and then you measure the
initial volume, then you drop the
object in the liquid, it will displace.
that liquid, right?
So now that displacement is
the volume of your object.
So one thing that you had to do is you
had to take that final volume, minus
it by your initial, and then plug
it into your density formula, right?
So grams over that displacement.
And that would allow you to do density.
So one thing that when we do this,
right, you have to make sure that
the volume is high enough to submerge
your object, but not too high where
like it goes over your tick marks.
So keep that in mind, right?
This is something that is
doable in four minutes, right?
For you to quickly fill the grad
cylinder, maybe put something in it.
This is doable.
Same thing with measuring
an object, right?
And calculating the volume.
Now, keep in mind the formulas
would be given to you if you had
a cylinder or a rectangle, but you
still need to know what density is.
That's something that probably wouldn't
be given to you because you should
know it because you've been using it
pretty much for most of the semester.
So let's say if I were to do a simple,
simple problem to figure this out.
So let's say I did give you a piece
of solid material and you weighed
it and you found out it weighed 422.
1234 grams.
So, and then you decide to place
the object into 50 milliliters
of water in a grad cylinder.
The water rises to a volume of 78.
2 milliliters.
What is the density?
So the first thing you're going
to do is remember, it's mass
over volume is your density.
So when we are trying to do that, the
first thing we're going to do is we're
going to put that mass that was measured,
and we're going to put that on top.
And then we're going to divide
it by the displaced volume.
So being that it's always final
minus initial, so we had 78.
2 milliliters as our final, right?
And then our initial was 50.
0 milliliters.
So we'll take those, put them in our
denominator, and that's something
that's going to be subtracted.
So now once we do that, we
subtract those, we divide 422.
1234 divided by 28.
2, which is that difference.
What you're going to get is 14.
9689 grams per ml, right?
So that's what you'd want to write.
You want to write your
units and your number.
Now the thing is, did
I get it right though?
So yes, my calculator spitted that
value out and sure, that's what it said.
It must be right.
Thing is though, you have to be
aware of how to round it too.
So we got to look at our sig figs.
So you can see that the mass had
a ton of sig figs, or seven here.
But the volumes were down to three, so
we always go off our lowest sig figs.
So what we would have to do
is round it to 3 sig figs.
So right under the 9 here.
So what it's going to be
is 15 grams per milliliter.
And I include my units.
You box off your answer so that
your professor can find it easily.
So that way it shows your work and the
other thing to keep in mind is you want to
include all your work, even if you get the
wrong answer, include your work, it could
award you a lot of partial credit points,
especially if you were on the right
track when you were doing this problem.
Now, the key thing to keep
and look out for is make sure
you did displacement, right?
It's called the displacement
method for a reason.
Make sure you subtract your volumes.
That's usually the thing
that people forget the most.
Let's go on to our next lab.
Now the electrons and atoms lab is
something that you have probably have not
even thought about in about three months.
Now with this one, the whole idea behind
it was you were looking at all these
different lamp sources using this little
spectroscope that you held up to your
eyes and essentially showed you like
this little rainbow on the spectrum.
Now with this one, there's not
a lot in it that's actually
doable in four to five minutes.
So So this is where you got to
kind of be strategic with how
you're what you're studying and
especially how much time do you have?
So the one thing that you could do
is you could use a spectroscope,
you could maybe draw what spectra
you saw, you could even maybe label
different wavelengths that are seen.
Now, one thing I put up here is you
have to understand the Bohr model
too, in case maybe you had a label
like increasing energy, increasing
wavelength, maybe frequency.
Those are things that are doable.
Um, there were a couple of
formulas you used back then.
One of them was the Bohr for, sorry,
not the, the, um, the Rydberg equation.
You will probably never have
to use that on the practical.
It takes a long time to use it.
It's something that's a little hard
to use in introductory chemistry.
Um, so I wouldn't recommend reviewing
it, but I would keep in mind, like,
make sure you know how to use.
your energy formulas, your wavelength
formulas, your speed of light,
just because they are quicker
calculations that you can do easily.
So like maybe an example, like if I look
at the C is equal to lambda times, uh,
the frequency, which is nu, Well, one
easy thing you could do is like, maybe
you got to measure a wavelength and
then you got to calculate frequency.
Um, speed of light is always a constant.
So maybe you could have to plug
in some values or maybe you
measure a wavelength and you have
to figure out the energy there.
There's all kinds of little things
that are possible to calculate
depending on what it is that's here.
Um, now at this lab, typically, It's
generally going to be an easier question.
If it's something that's given
to you, being that most of it is.
more of a physics lab
than a chemistry lab.
So let's go take a look at our next one.
Experiment 5A was the Empirical Formula
Lab, which was probably one of your
first more difficult workup labs
because it tied in the concept of the
mole empirical formulas, molecular
formulas, a ton of new equipment.
It was kind of like your first real
chemistry experiment that you had to do.
So the first thing that's a very
common question that could come
out of this one is recognizing
your glassware and equipment.
So one thing you got to keep in
mind is generally on the first
page of your lab manual after the
table of contents, Is a list of
what all the equipment looked like.
Now they're drawings.
They're not the best pictures, but
it's something to study off of.
So making flashcards with the pictures
and the names can be really helpful.
It's the easier question that if
you have that one, you want to get
right, especially if it's worth
five points or 10 points, depending
on what your questions are worth.
You want to answer those ones, especially
if like maybe your, your strongest
suit is not the math part, or maybe
you don't know how to do pH or you
don't know how to do something, right?
You need to, you need to make sure you
get these points or the easier points.
So a couple of things that
we learned about, right?
We learned about the Bunsen burner.
So that's on the far left here.
So that should be familiar.
Um, other things we use a lot,
we use ring stands all the time.
So if you had identified that,
uh, clay triangles are, were
used to hold our crucibles on.
So if you kind of remember this
guy sat on top of the triangle.
And then that went on top
of the Bunsen burner flame.
Um, we also had iron rings
that we used as well.
So like the triangle would
sit on the iron ring.
So just kind of remembering that these
things exist, there was the crucible
tongs, which were used to take this off.
Cause you remember your fingerprints
never wanted to be on it.
And then you had the wire mesh that you
could sit that on to help cool it down.
So there was a lot of things.
Now, with this experiment,
this experiment took 15 minutes
just for one iteration of it.
And you had to do it two
or three times to heat it.
So the whole experiment
took about an hour.
You're not going to
have to do that, right?
That's not something doable
in four to five minutes.
But recognizing things is
doable in four to five minutes.
Now, other things to keep in mind, like
what other questions could you ask?
Doing an empirical or molecular
formula is the main goal of this
lab, but it's something that
is a very tricky calculation.
It might take, this would be
your hard question if you had it.
So depending on your version, you might.
So, if that's the case, I would
recommend going to my empirical
and molecular formula video.
It's a 16 minute video if you want
to kind of just fast forward to the
part where I go through an example
and I try to actually base it off
this experiment when I made the video.
So that way you were a little
bit more ready for that lab
when you were getting to it.
Other things you might have to
do is the molar mass, right?
Can you find a molar mass?
Can you find a number of moles?
Can you do those basic
stoichiometry calculations?
Because if you can't do those,
that's really concerning
towards your professor, right?
You need to know the
basics in order to pass.
Um, another thing that we also did in
that lab in the post lab is there was
a lot of percent composition questions,
which was how much of a molecule is this
particular element or this particular
ion or whatever contained inside of this.
So that's another thing that
it would be worth your while to
refresh yourself and how to do this
part over the whole calculations.
for a formula because it will help
you study for your final exam as well.
So, let's go look at the next lab.
Now, when it comes to molecular modeling,
which was experiment 6, this was one
of the earliest labs you had to do
where you first started to learn about
how chemicals are bonded together.
So, the only thing you could
essentially pull from this lab
is how to draw a Lewis structure.
So, this could come in
a couple different ways.
One, you could be given the
chemical formula and you have
to draw the Lewis structure.
The other one is maybe you're given the
model, and you have to draw what the
Lewis structure would be of the model.
Um, depending on your teacher, you
might have also had to identify
the VSEPR structure, but if that is
something you have to do, you would
be given a reference sheet to help
you identify the actual geometry.
Um, but let's say if, if you had to,
let's practice this real quick, cause
it may be, it's probably been a while
since you had to do Lewis structures.
So the first thing you had to do is find
the central atom, which I always like
to say is what has the most friends.
So looking at your bonding trends,
oxygen can make up to two bonds.
Hydrogen can make one.
So in that case, oxygen
can have more friends.
So when you draw this, the
first thing you're going to do
is you're going to place all of
its valence electrons around it.
Oxygen has six valence electrons,
so we're going to add six dots
all around that structure.
Now the next thing we're going to do
is we're going to place the hydrogens.
And you always want to put the bonds
in line with where those single dots
are, because your goal is a pair.
So we're going to put a
hydrogen on the bottom here.
and then a hydrogen on the left.
And if you drew this and you put
them in another spot that's fine
as long as it's showing that the,
that each hydrogen has one valence
electron and they're on their own.
Now the next thing you're going
to do is you're going to connect
all these different bonds.
So we have one bond that's right here
and then we have another one on the side.
Now after you do that you want
to count to make sure you have
all your valence electrons.
Right.
So we have eight valence
electrons for this molecule
before we connected everything.
So when you're doing this, you
just want to kind of double check,
make sure you got everything right.
We have one, two, three, four,
five, six, then seven and eight.
So everything's accounted for.
We have a correct structure.
Now with CO2, once again, a lot of times
that the central atom is written first.
So in this case, carbon is your central.
So carbon has four valence
electrons around it, so we're
going to write those four dots.
And then what we're going to do is
we're going to place our oxygens
on each side, just to kind of
make it a little symmetrical.
And then we're going to add the
six dots on each oxygen because
it has six valence electrons.
So we got that.
Now the thing about these is
if you remember is that you all
want to obey the octet rule.
So we'll connect everything
with a single line first.
And what you're going to see is
nothing obeys that rule of eight.
The carbons don't, the oxygen, oxygen
stones, they're all really mad.
So what we're going to do
is we're going to make.
Double bonds first to see, hey, can
you make everything more satisfied?
And when we make one double bond, it
makes the oxygen on the right happy.
And then let's say if we make
a double bond on the left, it's
also going to make that happy.
They all have eight now
that they're all sharing.
Carbon has four.
It's giving four electrons via bonding
and it's receiving four as bonding.
So it has all eight.
And then you see the two lone pairs
around oxygen, and then you have the
four that are being shared in the double
bond, so it has its complete structure.
So this would be how you draw the
Lewis structure for both water and CO2.
Let's look at our next lab.
The calorimetry experiment was also a very
data heavy lab, which had a lot of workup.
The good thing about the calorimetry lab,
I guess, is that it was actually fast.
So meaning it's something that is
doable within a five minute period,
because all you were doing was
mixing different solutions together
and seeing, is there a heat change?
So there was a couple of different
things that were possible.
Now with calorimetry, if you don't
really remember it really well, I did
make a video just on calorimetry and I
did try to title it lab based examples
because I went through very similar
examples to what you did in the lab
to try to help you with calculations.
And So with this thing, the whole
idea is being able to recognize
first what the system looked like.
So this one, we had two coffee cups, which
were sitting in nested in each other.
And then we had a little
cardboard lid on the top here.
And what you did is you mixed
a bunch of solutions together.
You would mix them together and you'd be
measuring what the temperature change was.
Whether the temperature went
up or went down told you
some stuff about the science.
So, what are some things that I can
think of that you would need to know?
So, the first one is, well, make sure
you really know how to use the MCAT
equation, which I wrote up here, right?
Knowing M is mass, C was the specific
heat, which usually probably a
lot of you forgot about that.
That was how much heat is
required to heat up one gram of a
substance by one degree Celsius.
So, and then times that by
the change in temperature.
So that is something you have to do,
and we'll go through an example of that.
Now I would recommend knowing
your units for this one.
Mass is in grams, C is usually in
joules over grams over Celsius,
and then T is in Celsius.
Now with, make sure you know how
to read a thermometer, right?
Once again, tick marks and
sig figs are important.
They will ding you on wrong answers
when it comes to answering these.
Now, the other thing is knowing how
to do a change in temperature, right?
Whenever we have a delta, that's
a displacement or a difference.
So that's final minus initial, right?
It's always in that order.
Now the other thing is to keep in mind
is remember exothermic and endothermic.
If the temperature goes up, meaning
it's releasing heat, it's exothermic.
If the temperature is getting
colder, that means it's absorbing
heat and it's going down, right?
So that's what you're going to observe.
when you're looking at those numbers.
So the big thing is like, know
how one thing that's easier to do
is like, maybe you might have to
make this and do it observations.
But another one is, can you manipulate the
data, which is usually the harder part.
So when it comes to trying to
calculate these, right, you might
be given a data set and you need to
be, and you're told solve for heat.
Could you do it, right?
So you got to be given the values.
So the first thing is you always take
your total mass of the solution, so that
will be your mass in that MCAT equation.
So we have QMC delta T.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to take our mass,
which in this case is 40.
1234 grams.
We're going to multiply
that by C, which is 4.
184 joules grams C, and you want to write
down all of your units while you do this,
so that way you get the maximum number
of points while you're going through it.
And then you're going to write down
times Celsius, and then you're going
to notice that, hey, your units
are cancelling, so that's going to
give you an idea that you're doing
these correctly, so that's good.
So once you multiply 40.
1234 times 4.
184 times 30, you're
going to get about 5036.
33.
Joules.
So once again, is this a correct answer?
Technically, from your calculator, yes.
But we need to show the correct sig figs.
So one thing you'll always look for
is the one with the smallest number.
So we have three sig figs
from your temperature.
So we got to round it to three sig figs.
So what this is going to be is
5040 joules, or you can show it in
kilojoules or scientific notation,
whichever one, you know, it makes
essentially like makes you happy here.
So I'm sure all of them will be accepted.
But it just kind of depends on
which one you want to aim for.
Let's look at our next experiment.
All right, experiment 11 B, which is
the termination of the gas constant.
So with this one, it's one that like a
lot of people tend to forget about just
because it's been a minute and it also
was a very, very quick experiment too.
So it only lasted about 45 minutes.
So with this one, it's something
that takes a little too long once
again for you to physically do it.
But there is a lot of measurements
that you could take in this one.
One of the easy ones, once
again, is the thermometer.
Make sure you're able to read it.
The other one is know how to use
a gas collection tube, right?
So, if you remember, you had a big
tube that what you had in it was
magnesium inside of it, and when it
reacted with HCl, it made a ton of gas.
The gas pushed out the water,
and then you measured the
volume of gas that was in here.
So make sure you're comfortable
in reading that volume.
It's in milliliters, so keep that in mind.
Know your, know your units, so you know
how to read those, those different pieces.
Now there was a couple other things that
we used in order to read things too.
One of them is being that this
was a gas law lab, you have
to measure pressure, right?
So we got to be comfortable with that.
Remember, there's a bunch of units for it.
There was, uh, millimeters of mercury,
there was torr, there was atmospheres.
So I'd recommend kind of
refreshing yourself with that.
The most common in our class were
atmosphere and millimeters of mercury.
So make sure you're comfortable
with going between those two units.
Now with them we used a couple different
reference materials to measure pressure.
The one is we had a digital pressure gauge
which told you the pressure of the room.
The other one is we had a book that
told us what the pressure of, uh,
water or the partial pressure of
water inside of this container.
So I would recommend going through and
reviewing those different concepts.
So you, you might have
to use the ideal gas law.
Because you can figure out the pressure
from the different, maybe the scales,
the volume from the tube, the temperature
from a thermometer, they're all things
that could be put in front of you, right?
Now, the one hard part is making sure
you remember how to use Dalton's Law.
So, usually you want to use whatever
your gas is as one of the pressures,
and generally the other one is water.
Which is where that book came from.
So what I would really recommend is
there's a lot of videos that I kind
of made that use this concept, um,
being that it does tie into gases.
It's possible to see gas
stoichiometry in this as well.
Um, I would recommend kind of reviewing
percent yields too, just because
it's something that can get tied in.
So there's kind of a few
things you could review.
One could be the ideal gas law,
uh, Dalton's law for sure, just
because this is probably one of
the more comprehensive videos.
It's kind of, it tied
these two things together.
So this one is a really
good, uh, bet for reviewing.
And then there was a two
stoichiometry videos, which I
released like a few weeks ago.
So with these two, right,
there's part one and part two.
Part two has to do with the ideal gas
law, so that's more relevant to this lab.
Um, and then percent yield is if you have
to figure out a theoretical yield or how
much was made and how much was collected.
You had to do these more in class
in terms of calculations, but it
is an important concept in lab two.
Okay, so let's look at our next or sorry.
Let's look at our next example with
our next one, which was experiment
nine This one took a you had to make a
standard solution scheme just like the
one that was in your lab manual, right?
You had to Take the densities
and plot it against molarity
values, which you've found.
So the first thing is,
you need to know molarity.
Like, there's no way around that.
That's one of the things I've
been trying to say, like,
for weeks in terms of videos.
Moles over liters.
You have to know how to do it.
Because we've done probably about three
or four labs that involve molarity.
Um, the dilution formula was a big thing.
Right?
If you have a solution and it's way,
it has, it's way too concentrated,
meaning like I was using an analogy,
it's too sweet or too salty.
So what do you do?
You add water to it to dilute it.
So that was something
that was really common.
You had to This is a formula that's
generally assumed that you know
off the top of your head, just so
you know, because M1V1 equals M2V2
is a very, very common formula.
So especially if you are someone that
makes solutions in chemistry, bio, or
health sciences, it is very common.
So sometimes this formula is not given.
It's probably one of the
few that's not given.
So I would recommend just knowing
it off the top of your head, it
will help you, um, be comfortable
in how to make solutions and how,
what was involved with using them.
So the big thing is we use
the volumetric flask, right?
So knowing how to use it,
how to identify it, right?
It has a teardrop shape to it.
So you can kind of see like
the teardrop bottom here.
We had two kinds of pipettes.
There's a transfer pipette, which
is just for moving liquids around.
You don't use it to measure.
Then you have your volumetric
pipette, which was always
labeled with the actual volume.
And that one was a very
precise piece of glassware.
If you remember, it went
down to two decimal places.
That's really important to realize.
Um, and then we went through density,
molarity, we made a calibration
curve, so there's all kinds of
things that could be used here.
Um, being that we talked about density
earlier, uh, and we also kind of, we'll do
a little bit of molarity in a little bit.
Uh, let's talk about how
to use that curve, right?
So this was one of the things
that you had to plot, right?
So you took the time to make
it and you had to use it.
So you had to, uh, measure an
unknown, uh, mall or sorry, solution.
And you figured out its density.
If we do this example in ISU, what
is the molarity of a solution with 1.
021 grams per milliliter as its density?
How would you solve it?
What would you do here?
So the thing about this curve,
right, is how is it all labeled?
Well, you got to kind of remember, right,
we have the y axis, which was on the left
hand side, and then we had the x axis.
So what we were given is we
were given a density, right?
That's a y value.
Now, one thing about this is you notice
that there's this line that's going up
and up and down the, uh, the actual graph.
That's referring to this Y equals MX plus
B formula, which is something you can
use to find the concentration, right?
Because you notice there's
an X value and a Y value.
So what you can do is you can
plug your value into that.
So what we have is 1.
021 grams over ml, and that's
going to be equal to the other
part of the formula, which is 0.
0435 x plus 0.
9984.
So what you would do is rearrange
this equation and solve for x.
So if we were to do that, and we
were to solve for x, Just like so,
so we're going to subtract our 0.
9984 and then divide by our 0.
435, that would get x by itself.
So when you solve for that, what
you are going to end up getting as
a number is you're going to get your
molarity, which is going to be 0.
5195 molar.
And this is something else you can round
to sig figs, so being that everything was
four sig figs in the data table, you would
end up rounding this to four sig figs.
So this is the idea, right?
Can you manipulate data?
Can you read data?
That's important, right?
Because you've been doing it all semester.
So you got to be confident in it.
And like I've been saying, like,
if you've been doing your labs,
you've been doing the work.
You will get a good grade you just but
it's you still got a review for it You
don't want to go into and be like, oh,
I got a hundred on every lab, but I
failed the practical That's crazy, right?
You need to practice your skills.
So let's go to the next one.
The next one was types of reactions
So experiment 10a was a very very
intensive data workup lab It was
really fun kind of going around mixing
things together for about an hour
But the one thing you notice is that
the data workup for this took hours.
You had to write all these net
ionic equations, predict all these
reactions, balance all of them.
But there were skills that you
need for this class, right?
You're using them all the
time in stoichiometry.
So you still use them and doesn't go away.
So the first thing you got to
make sure you're familiar with
is know your types of reactions.
Can you predict your reactions?
And this is something sadly you do
not get notes or a reference for.
So you need to kind of know
at least the fundamentals.
Can you do a combination decomposition,
double replacement, single displacement?
Can you do them?
Um, the other thing you need to be
familiar with is the scheme too, based
on observations of what you're seeing.
So, like, did a gas come off of it?
Gas evolution.
Did a solid form?
That's precipitation.
So, that way you know how
to label things correctly.
You will have to predict
products and label the reactants.
Can you balance it?
If I give you a complete form, if I give
you the whole formula, can you balance it?
Um, can you label the states of
matter based off what you saw?
Or can you write a net ionic equation if
I give you the solubility rules, right?
Now, even though this is not in this lab,
all this stuff, these skills will lead
to stoichiometry, which is essentially
the pinnacle of the course, right?
It all leads up to stoichiometry,
which ties everything together.
So can you try to relate
all these things together?
So I put a solubility table here
because one thing that we're going
to practice real quick is can you
write a net ionic equation, right?
So can we do the whole
process from start to finish?
So the first thing is, right, is you
want to write down your reactants of
what's going to be mixing together.
So we have barium chloride
and then sodium sulfate.
is here, and what they're
going to be doing is mixing
together to make a new compound.
So the first thing we always do is
we assign our letters to each ion.
So barium is ion, chlorine is an ion,
we have sodium, and then sulfate.
So it's AB plus CD.
So what is that?
That's going to be a double
replacement reaction.
So what we're going to have bond together
is the inside is going to bond and then
the outside is going to bond together.
Now the thing to remember,
cation is always written first.
So we'll take sodium.
We do not write the subscript here.
We just bring the ion, And then
we same thing with chlorine
will bring that over as well.
So just the ion.
So notice how they're, they're
balanced with their charges.
So we don't have to worry about swap drop.
And then we'll bring
over barium and sulfate.
So B a.
SO4, and that's 2 plus and
2 minus, so that's balanced
in terms of charge as well.
Now the next part is we're going
to do our, balance our formula.
So you'll notice is that there's
two sodiums and two chlorines on the
left, so what we're going to do is put
two on the right, and now we have a
balanced complete molecular equation
once we remove all those charges.
Now the next part is using
your solubility rules.
So the first thing is that we have
barium chloride and sodium sulfate.
So one thing you'll see is if we
look for our different ions, so we
have chlorine here and then sulfate.
It says chlorine is soluble
except when it's bound to some
heavy metals, so that one's good.
And then we have sulfate is
soluble except when it's bound
to calcium, strontium, or barium.
So it's soluble is sodium, but not
with barium, which was our other one.
So with these, what we can see is,
is what was soluble is the barium.
Chloride is aqueous,
sodium sulfate was aqueous.
Uh, sodium chloride is aqueous.
But our last one, which was the barium
sulfate, is a solid, that one's insoluble.
So now we're going to break
everything down into its ions.
So the barium will break down into an
ion, so we put barium 2 and we'll have
two chlorines, and two so sodiums.
It's like we're smashing all these pieces
because they are soluble in water, right?
So everything's breaking down.
And then the only thing that stays
together are solids and gases.
They stay together.
So now when we have that, oops, Uh,
when those things stay together,
you will pretty much, you're
going to leave them there for the
very last part of the reaction.
So we're canceling out anything
that's a spectator, that's
identical on the left and the right.
So the things that you'll see is
that, okay, there's two chlorines,
there's two sodiums, they're
the same, they're just watching.
So everything else stays
in the net ionic equation.
So there's barium, sulfate.
And then there's, that's all leading
to barium sulfate, and that's how you
would write a net ionic equation, right?
Of all those pieces of the
puzzle from start to finish.
This is a longer one, so if you
had to do this one, this would be
your hard problem for your, for
your example is doing a net ionic
equation because it takes a long time.
So let's go to our next one.
So with experiment 12a with
the pH of household chemicals.
The whole idea here is you need to be
able to understand the basics of pH and
how to do the different calculations
behind them, and also understand how
to use red cabbage as an indicator
or realistically any indicator.
So can you calculate
pH POHH three oh plus?
OH minus?
Can you calculate all these little
pieces and use all these formulas?
Now, the thing about this, you will be
given these formulas if you have to use
them, so, but you need to be able to
like read a chart that looks like this.
So if I were to, let's say, do one
of these, let's say I want you to
solve for P O H, O H minus, and
H 3O plus, and I give you the pH.
So if we start up here in the top
right corner, we can follow any
road to get to the other pieces.
And So, for example, if I have pH,
the easiest one to solve for is pOH.
All you need to do is take 14 minus 4.
30, which was our pH, and then
we would get our pOH as 9.
70.
So we have one of the parts.
Now from there, in order to go from
either pH or pOH to its concentration.
We need to do 10 to the negative, uh,
either 10 to the negative pH or 10 to the
negative EOH to solve for the other parts.
Now with these, the
hardest part is sig figs.
So if you kind of remember, if
there's two decimal places, that
means you have two sig figs.
So in this case, what we're going to end
up having for the one on the left is 5.
0 times 10 to the negative 5
is going to come out as your
molarity for the left one.
And yeah, And then on the
other, you're going to have 2.
0 times 10 to the negative
10 molarity on the right.
So these would be all of your values
for this problem if you had to solve it.
And it's something
that's quick and doable.
You have your calculator to do
them, but you have to be familiar
with how to use those formulas.
Let's go on to our last one.
All right, so experiment 12b, which was
the one that we've done the most recently,
the big thing about this is this probably
should be the freshest one in your
brain, so you should be familiar with
how to do it for the practical and best.
Um, with this one, there were, there was
a lot that was being done in this lab.
The first thing is knowing
your glassware, right?
The first thing is we had some new piece
of glassware, we had a burette, and then
we also had an Erlenmeyer flask, that
was the first time you were using those.
So make sure you're able to identify
them and to know how to read them, right?
Especially the burette you have to
know how to read an initial and a
final volume how to read how much was
used That's a big part of this now.
There is some vocabulary that was
introduced in the introduction So the
first thing is there's the word titration
meaning that you're taking an acid and
base you're canceling them out There can
be other chemicals, but in our case, it's
an acid and base There's one word that,
in lab, that I mentioned to some students,
not everybody, but it's the word titrant.
This is the chemical that you know
the volume and the molarity of.
So for us, that was sodium hydroxide.
Um, standardization was what
we did to find that molarity.
So that's another concept in
being familiar with those terms.
Um, we had to find a
molar mass of a hydrate.
So that's something that kind of makes
refresh your brain on in case you forgot.
Um, I do have a in my molar mass video.
I do go over that.
Um, make sure you know how to
read that initial and final.
Um, know the volume you use and be able
to perform solution stoichiometry, right?
So if you were, um, not to, uh, maybe to,
uh, versed on stoichiometry, if you're
behind, I really should look at some of
the stoichiometry videos before the, the
actual, um, uh, before the test, just
because, you know, there's going to be at
least one of those, uh, problems you're
going to get is going to be stoichiometry,
at least one station will be.
So you have to do something either
whether it's mass to mass or solution to
solution, there's going to be something.
So these two videos that were recent,
the one was acid base titration,
and then solution stoichiometry
that you can view as well.
So, with our last example, that to cover
the rest of the video, um, if I ask you
what is the molarity of sodium hydroxide,
if 25 milliliters is combined with 0.
1000 grams of acetic acid?
So with these, the big thing
is you got to be able to kind
of remember your mole maps.
So the first thing is, like, you
got to ask yourself is, well,
which one can I get to moles with?
Can I do it with a mass or with a volume?
The only one that you
actually can is a mass.
So if I have a mass of, let's say, an acid
in this case, the way that we can convert
that to moles Is using the molar mass.
So if I have molar mass, which we were
given, we can convert from mass to moles.
So let's put that down.
So we have 0.100 grams of acetic
acid, so H-C-H-H-C two, H 3 0 2.
And what we're gonna cancel
that out is the molar mass.
Okay?
So we have 60.021 grams
equivalent to one mole.
of our acetic acid.
Now the next part is, well, how do we
get two moles of our sodium hydroxide?
Well, this is where the chemical
formula comes into play.
So one thing you'll notice is
that it's a one to one ratio.
So what we can write is that we
have one mole of acetic acid, so
HC2H3O2, and that's equivalent
to one mole of sodium hydroxide.
Now the thing is, though,
you're done because you need
to figure out Your molarity.
This is where earlier I said
you gotta know molarity, right?
It's moles over liters.
So we're gonna solve for the
moles of sodium hydroxide.
So once we do 0.
1 divided by 60.
021, you're gonna get 0.
001666 moles of sodium hydroxide, and
then we're gonna divide that by our
volume, which was 25 milliliters, and
we're gonna convert that to liters.
So we have 25 mLs.
We'll quickly convert that to liters, and
then we'll divide by that, by that number.
And what we're going
to end up getting is 0.
06664 molarity of sodium hydroxide.
And the thing about that is you could
solve for pH, you could do all that
stuff too, but that would be a really
long, a little bit of a longer problem.
So we're not going to
do that in this video.
So that's in my other videos.
Okay, this was a very long review
video, but hopefully it does help some
of you, those of you who were able to
grunt through it and make it through it.
Um, I tried to go through a little
bit of everything with all of it.
So it's my first time trying to make
a review video for all this stuff.
Um, so try to study hard.
I hope that this did help a little bit.
And please let me know if you need help
until you're, um, until you're practical.
and either reach out via email,
discord, comment below, whatever
you need to get ahold of me.
Okay.
All right, y'all.
I hope you have a wonderful
day and I'll see y'all later.
Bye now.